<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.hcmc.uvic.ca/job/MoEML/lastStableBuild/artifact/static/site/xml/schemas/london_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Marlowe_Ovid_Elegy_1_Hawkes">
    <!-- 
    Caroline Hawkes
    12/09/2022
    Marlowe's Ovid, Elegy 4
    Used A and B text
    
-->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Marlowe_Ovid</title>
                <author><persName type="hist"><forename><surname/></forename></persName></author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Printed by <persName type="hist"><forename/>
                    <surname/></persName>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source
                    <!-- Working from Huntington Library (microfilm) copy available via EEBO and Boston Public Library --><idno>STC
                        21864</idno></p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>TEI P5</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="BENN"/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- COMMENT IT OUT -->
    <text>
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">
                        <fw type="header" style="text-align:center; font-style: italic"><hi style="font-size=150%">OVIDS ELEGIES.</hi></fw>
                        <hi style="text-align: center; font-style: italic;">
                            ELEGIA. 4. <!-- Translation: Elegy 4--> <lb/>
                            Amicam, qua arte, quibuſue nutibus in cans preſente <!-- Translation:  I am a friend, with what art, with every nod to the present dog--> <lb/>
                            viro vts debeat, admonet. <!-- Translation: it is due to the husband, he warns. --> <lb/>
                        </hi>
                        <lb/>
                    </titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docAuthor/>
                <docImprint/>
                <docDate/>
            </titlePage>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section">
                <lg>
                    <l>
                        THy husband to a banquet goes with me, <lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Pray God it may his lateſt ſupper be. <lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Shall I ſit gazing as a baſhfull gueſt,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        While others touch the damſel I loue beſt?<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        With lying, vnder him his boſome clippe?<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        About thy neck ſhall he at pleaſure skippe?<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Marueile not, though the faire Bride did incite, <lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        The drunken <hi style="font-style:italic">Centaures</hi> to a ſodaine fight. <lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        I am no halfe horſe, hor in woods I dwell, <lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Yet ſcarſe my hands from thee contain: I well.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        But how thou ſhould'ſt behaue thy ſelſe now know<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Nor let the windes a way my warnings blow.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Before thy husband come, though I not ſee,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        What may be done, vet there before him * <!-- Second Version Translation --> be.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Lye with him gently, when his limbes * <!-- Second Version Translation --> he ſpread, <lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Vpon the bed, but on my feete firſt tread. <lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        View me, my becks, and ſpeaking couatenance, * <!-- Second Version Translation --><lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Take, and receiue each ſecret amorous glaunce. * <!-- Second Version Translation --><lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Words without voyce ſhall on my eye-browes ſit,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Lines thou ſhalt read in wyne by my hand writ.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        When our laſciuious toyes come in * <!-- Second Version Translation --> thy minde,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Thy Roſie checks * <!-- Second Version Translation --> be to thy thombe inc<hi style="font-style:italic">linde.</hi><lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        If ought of me thou ſpeak'it in inward thought,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Let thy ſoft finger to thy eare be brought.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        When I (my light) do or ſay ought that pleaſe thee. <lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Turne round thy gold-ring, as it were to eaſe thee. <lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Strike on the boord * <!-- Second Version Translation, not clear --> like them that pray for euill,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        When thou doeſt wiſh thy husband as the deuil.<lb/>
                    </l>
                        <fw type="signature">A 4<supplied reason="omitted-in-original">r</supplied></fw>
                        <fw type="catchword" style="text-align;right;">What</fw> <lb/>
                        <pb/>
                        <fw type="header" style="text-align:center; font-style: italic"><hi style="font-size=150%">OVIDS ELEGIES.</hi></fw>
                    <l>
                        What wine he fills thee, wiſely will him drinke,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Aske thou the boy, what thou enough doeſt thinke.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        When thou haſt taſted, I will take the cup,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        And where thou drink'ſt, on that part I will ſup.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        If he giues thee what firſt himſelſe did taſt,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        If he giues thee what firſt himſelſe did taſt,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Euen in his face his offered Goblets caſt.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Let not thy neck by his vile armes be preſt,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Nor leaue thy ſoſt head on his boiſtrous breſt.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Thy boſomes Roſeat buds let him not finger,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Chiefely on thy lips let not his lips linger. <lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        If thou giueſt kiſſes, I ſhall all diſcloſe,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Say they are mine, and hands on thee impoſe.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Yet this I'le ſee, but if thy gowne ought couer,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Suſpitious feare in all my veines will houer.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Mingle not thighes, nor to his legge ioyne thine,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Nor thy ſoſte foote with his hard foote combine.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        I haue beene wanton, therefore am perplext,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        And with miſtruſt of the like meaſure vext.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        I and my wench oft vnder clothers did lurke,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        When pleaſure mou'd  vs to our ſweeteſt worke.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Do not thou ſo, but throw thy mantle hence,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Leaſt I ſhould thinke thee guilty of offence.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Entreat thy husband drinke, but do not kiſſe,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        And while he drinks, to adde more do not miſſe,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        If he lyes downe with wine and ſleepe opreſt,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        The thing and place ſhall counſell vs the reſt.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        When to goe home wards we riſe all along,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Haue care to walke in middle of the throng.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        There will I finde thee or be found by thee,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        There touch what euer thou canſt touch of me.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Aye me I warne what profits ſome few howers,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        But we muſt part, when heau'n with black night lowers <lb/>
                    </l>
                        <fw type="signature"><supplied reason="omitted-in-original">A 4v</supplied></fw>
                        <fw type="catchword" style="text-align;right;">At</fw> <lb/>
                        <pb/>
                        <fw type="header" style="text-align:center; font-style: italic"><hi style="font-size=150%">OVIDS ELEGIES.</hi></fw>
                    <l>
                        At night thy husband clippes, I will weepe<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        And to the dores ſight of thy ſelſe keepe,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Then will he kiſſe thee, and not onely kiſſe,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        But force thee giue him my ſtolne honey bliſſe.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Conſtrain'd againſt thy will giue it the pezants<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Forebeare ſweet wordes, and be your ſport vnpleaſant.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        To him I pray it no delight may bring,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        Or if it do to thee no ioy thence ſpring.<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        But though this night thy fortune be to trie it,<lb/>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        To me to morrow conſtantly deny it. 
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>